Now listen to part of a classroom lecture on geographical and related characteristics of Greece and answer questions 31 to 40.
You have some time to look at questions 31 to 40.
Now listen to the lecture and answer questions 31 to 40.
Good morning students! Today we're going to continue our discussion of European countries.
As you know we've already covered the countries from Northern and Central Europe as well as most of the ones that lie along the Mediterranean.
Today I'm going to talk about Greece.
As you know, it is an ancient birthplace of one of the most predominant civilizations to exercise early influence on much of the Western world.
Now, when you think of Greece, you think of its antiquity and ancient civilization.
You think of Alexander the Great, Plato, Aristotle, Socrates and all the great philosophers.
You think of the Trojan War, the ancient Greek gods and everything in between.
Out of all the European countries we have discussed, Greece is perhaps the richest country in terms of culture and contributions to our modern society.
More so than the Romans, for the Romans took much of what was Greek and repainted in a Roman fashion.
Greece has been known since ancient times and is located in Southern Europe, specifically Southeastern Europe.
Athens is the capital of this country and it is located in the southwest of the mainland.
It is also, of course, one of Greece's largest cities.
Greece is situated at the intersection of three continents, Europe, Western Asia and Africa.
It is bordered by Albania in the northwest, Macedonia and Bulgaria to the north and Turkey to the northeast.
The Aegean Sea surrounds the east of the mainland, the Ionian Sea is to the west, the Mediterranean Sea is to the south
and the Adriatic lies in the northwest.
Greece has the largest coastline of all the countries of Europe and is the 11th longest in the world.
Because of its large number of islands, Greece contains a mountainous peninsular mainland with a land boundary of 1168 km.
Greece has many islands totaling around 6000. There are 230 that are inhabited.
The climate of Greece is classified into three types, Mediterranean, Alpine and temperate.
The temperatures in the Mediterranean rarely reach extremes and at times there is sparse snowfall in some areas.
The temperature climate is mainly marked by cold, damp winters and hot, dry summers.
One of the most prominent geographical features of Greece is the mountain range.
Greece is among a small number of countries that feature a large number of mountains within their territories.
Mount Olympus is the highest peak and has been believed to be the abode of the 12 Olympian gods of ancient Greece.
It is the fourth tallest peak in Europe and rises approximately 3000 m above sea level.
The Pindus mountain range runs from the northwest to southeast and is further extended to the Peloponnese range.
The Pindus range also runs underwater and crosses the Aegean Sea to form the Aegean Islands.
The largest of these islands, the island of Crete, is controlled by Greece.
Greece also has a large number of islands and islets that lie in the Aegean Sea.
The largest island, Crete, extends 250 km from east to west and is 55 km in width at its widest point.
It is approximately 150 km south of mainland Greece.
The Aegean Islands are a different cluster of seven different islands, six of which lie off the western coast.
The seventh lies off the southern tip of the Peloponnesian Mountains.
The Aegean Islands fill the Aegean Sea in an area that spans between mainland Greece to the west and north,
Anatolia to the east and Crete to the south.
While much of the climate of Greece is predominantly Mediterranean,
the Pindus mountain range divides the country so that the climate is much wetter in the west.
It is drier and windier in the east, particularly during the summers.
The northern areas have a transitional climate, while other areas have an alpine climate.
The average annual temperature varies between 10 to 19.7 degrees Celsius.
The winds in Greece are colloquially known as the Meltimi, but they are better known by the name Etzysians.
These are prominent in the Greek mainland from the mid-summers to early winter.
They keep the temperatures on the islands of the Aegean lower than those in the Ionian Sea.
Please be sure to check your answers.
That is the end of the listening test.